Welcome to session 12 of the Lam Rim.
And we've been talking about
the place that compassion has
in the five steps for getting to this
bodhisattva vision: bodhichitta.
And we reached the fifth
step, which is compassion.
And we kind of are pausing
here to see how compassion
is like the center of the propellor.
All the other steps of the seven steps,
they revolve around compassion.
Somehow, compassion is at the root of
beautiful love,
and at the root of recognizing the people
have been my mom, thinking
about what they did,
thinking to repay them.
Somehow, compassion is at the center
of all these seven steps for getting to
bodhichitta in the system
of Atisha, Lord Atisha.
So we're going to continue on that theme.
And ere at the beginning,
we're going to get a quotation
from Master Chandrakirti.
So Pabongka Rinpoche,
he's going to pull out a quotation
from Master Chandrakirti.
I've been working on a
great, great commentary
by Je Tsongkapa
on this book by Chandrakirti,
called "Entering the Middle Way."
And Tsongkapa's book is
called DGONGS PA RAB GSAL
which means clarifying or
illuminating the true thought
of Chandrakirti.
So, to get into this topic,
let's talk about about a special vision
that Je Tsongkapa had.
Here's a picture of it.
I wrote a long
history of Tsongkapa,
it took me many years.
This particular scene
is 1397.
You can see Je Tsongkapa
sitting at the bottom
in the yellow robe.
And he's having a vision.
I think, if my dating is
correct, it's the autumn
of 1397.
Je Tsongkapa goes into this awesome vision
where he sees all the great teachers
of emptiness in history,
the major teachers.
You can see here, Nagarjuna at the top,
and then we're going to have Buddhapalita
who wrote commentaries on Nagarjuna.
Then we're going to have
probably Bhavaviveka,
who complained about
Buddhapalita's commentary.
And then Chandrakirti,
who complained to
Bhavaviveka for complaining
about Buddhapalita's commentary.
So anyway, you're going to
have all the great teachers
of the emptiness lineage
here in this vision.
There's a tradition that says that
this is when Je Tsongkapa
saw emptiness directly.
So people often ask me,
was Je Tsongkapa an arya? And there is,
the only mention of the
question is in this scene,
in commentaries to this part of his life,
this moment in his life
that in conjunction with,
apparently he saw the Buddhapalita
written across the sky
or something.
And then they say that during that period,
he had the direct perception of emptiness.
So that's our tradition.
So I thought
since Pabongka Rinpoche
is going to explain
the role of compassion by going to
Chandrakirti's great book,
Entering the Middle Way,
why don't we go to
Je Tsongkapa's commentary on this verse,
because I've been working
on that commentary
about seven years and it's very cool.
So here we go.
DPAL LDAN ZLA BAS KYANG
The glorious Chandrakirti,
'JUG PA BRTZAMS PA'I THOG MAR
when he first started to
write his great classic
Madhyamaka Avatara,
Entering the Middle Way.
And by the way, Middle Way in that case
doesn't mean philosophical Middle Way,
it means Nagarjuna's
root text called Wisdom.
So Chandrakirti says
,GANG PHYIR BRTZE NYID RGYAL
BA'I LO TOG PHUN TSOGS 'DI'I,
,SA BON DANG NI SPEL LA
CHU 'DRA YUN RING DU,
,LONGS SPYOD GNAS LA SMIN
PA LTA BUR 'DOD GYUR PA,
,DE PHYIR BDAG GIS THOG MAR
SNYING RJER BSTOD PAR BGYI,
At the beginning
of his greatest book,
one of the greatest books
ever written on emptiness,
Chandrakirti, Master Chandrakirti,
does not bow down to emptiness,
and he does not bow down to wisdom,
and he does not bow down to bodhichitta.
He bows down to compassion.
And he says, there's a reason.
So it fits into the Lam Rim so sweetly
that the Lam Rim guy stole
that verse for Lam Rim.
So Chandrakirti says,
you want to understand emptiness?
Then get compassion.
Then everybody's like, "What?
I thought I was supposed to meditate on
shamata, vipashyana."
- No, get compassion.
Why and how? We're going
to go through it today.
That's what our goal is.
GANG PHYIR means because.
BRTZE NYID love and
love alone is the seed,
SA BON, in the second line.
For RGYAL BA'I LO TOG PHUN TSOGS 'DI'I,
for these luscious, generous
crops of the Buddhas.
And t's like the seed
for planting the crops of enlightenment.
But it's also like the water that you add.
So we had yesterday THOG MTHA' BAR GSUM.
I'm sure you guys remember.
THOG MTHA' BAR GSUM
Beginning, ending and in between.
So Chandrakirti is saying, "Look,
why is compassion the
center of the seven?"
Why did Tsongkapa present compassion
as the center of the seven
steps to bodhichitta?
Why did he present it as the central theme
or the middle of the whole machine?
He says, "Well, there's three reasons,
THOG MTHA' BAR.
In the beginning, you need compassion.
In the middle, you need compassion.
And at the end, you need compassion.
In his opening lines
of his famous book on emptiness,
Chandrakirti says, "It's like the seed,
it's like the water,
and it's like the fruit."
It's like the seed.
It's like the water.
And it's like the fruit.
The seed of the fruit tree that you plant
is like the water that
you pour on the tree
before it grows fruit.
Then it's like the
fruit that you can enjoy
once the tree grows and produces fruit.
So compassion has a place THOG MTHA' BAR
in the beginning of all
this process, like the seed;
in the middle of the process,
like watering your garden every day;
and then at the end of the process
like eating the fruits that
grow out of your garden.
Then Chandrakirti says,
"That's why I'm not bowing down to wisdom.
I'm not bowing down to emptiness.
At the beginning of my book,
I'm bowing down to compassion
because it's the seed, it's the water
and it's the fruit."
CHU 'DRA YUN RING DU, LONGS SPYOD GNAS LA
LONGS SPYOD GNAS LA means
and you're going to
enjoy it eating it later.
SMIN PA LTA BUR 'DOD GYUR PA
It's like the maturation of the fruit.
DE PHYIR -- for that reason,
BDAG GIS THOG MAR SNYING
RJE BSTOD PAR BGYI
I'm going to bow down to compassion.
All right, now I thought it would be fun,
since this Lam Rim is going so fast,
if we added some more stuff.
So let's go look at what
Tsongkapa has to say
about this verse by Chandrakirti.
Let's go look at Tsongkapa's explanation.
And again, I added this part.
This is DGONGS PA RAB GSAL.
Je Tsongkapa's "Illumination
of the True Thought".
And let's read it together.
Because this Lam Rim's going too fast.
We're going to finish in 15-20 years.
Let's slow it down a little bit.
GNYIS PA NI, BYANG CHUB KYI
SEMS DANG GNYIS SU MED PA'I
YE SHES GNYIS KYI RTZA BA
YANG SNYING RJE YIN PAS NA,
Look, there's two important
spiritual goals we have
with this book by Chandrakirti,
by Master Chandrakirti.
What are they?
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS
We want to get to that bodhisattva vision.
We want to get to the
Wish for enlightenment.
And we want the GNYIS SU MED PA'I YE SHES.
We want the indivisible wisdom,
the wisdom which is free of two things.
The wisdom which is free of two things.
People call it non-duality
or something like that.
I feel a little
uncomfortable with the word.
People think it means
when you see emptiness.
There's no me and there's no emptiness.
No duality.
I sink into the emptiness,
there's no perceiver
and there's no perceived.
And people say, "Oh, that's non-duality."
That's not non-duality.
Non-duality means discrepancy.
Discrepancy.
What's discrepancy mean?
It means
there's a difference between
the way this guy acts
and the way he really is.
There's a discrepancy.
He says he's
a Lam Rim teacher and he never meditates.
That's a discrepancy.
So discrepancy means
it looks like one way and
it's really a different way.
And that's what duality means in Buddhism.
It means discrepancy.
It means they don't match.
The way things are
and the way things look
don't match.
It looks like your husband
is upset in the kitchen
because he had a hard day at his job.
But what's really happening is you
yelled at your kids last night.
So they don't fit.
There's a discrepancy
between the way it looks
and the way it is.
When you catch the discrepancy,
when you realize
how hard was his job today has
nothing to do with his mood.
His mood is coming from how you
treated your kids last week.
Then you free yourself of this duality.
That's all.
The way it looks
and the way it really is
don't match.
That's called non-duality.
When you figure it out,
we call it non-dual wisdom.
It doesn't see two
different things anymore.
It sees one thing.
I yelled at my kids.
It doesn't see a husband who's upset
because he's hungry or
something like that.
Although husbands do get upset
when they're hungry, right?
At least this husband does.
So don't forget, when I say non-duality,
it means the way he looks
and he way he really is
are going to match now.
Non-duality.
Now they're going to match.
Oh, he's upset cause I
yelled at my kids last week.
Oh, now it matches up.
So he says two great
spiritual goals here are:
bodhichitta, the wish to become
a Buddha to help all beings,
dance between planets;
and this wisdom which no longer separates,
now this wisdom sees
what's really going on.
Then he says a interesting thing.
This is Chandrakirti.
This is the root of all
emptiness books in Tibet,
Chandrakirti.
And he says, the root of
those two is compassion.
Then we're like, "What?"
Okay, I understand the bodhichitta,
I understand that compassion
can be the root of
bodhichitta, I understand that.
That makes sense.
You got to have compassion,
step number five of the seven steps,
to get to this vision of a Bodhisattva.
Why does compassion lead
you to understand your
husband in the kitchen?
Now that part I don't get.
But Chandrakirti is insistent.
In the beginning lines of
my book about emptiness,
I'm not going to talk about emptiness.
I'm going to talk about
the cause of emptiness
because that's more important.
What's the cause? Compassion. What?
Well, can't a lower arhat see emptiness?
It gets confusing, right?
So we're going to explore
that in this class.
We're going to explore that in this class.
And I'm not going to tell you an answer.
I want you to think about it.
I want you guys to figure it out.
That's your homework for
the next 10 years or so.
Chandrakirti refuses
to bow down to wisdom.
He refuses to bow down to
the perception of emptiness.
He says, "No,
compassion is the cause of that
seeing emptiness directly.
So let's bow down to that."
And by the way, it's also
the cause of bodhisattva.
And by the way, he takes it one more step.
Compassion causes bodhichitta
and the perception of emptiness,
and they create arhats and Buddhas.
So he goes like that.
Compassion causes emptiness
understanding and bodhichitta,
and they create Buddhas and arhats.
Like that. He has a flow like that.
Now I'm going to read you Tsongkapa,
and you're going to figure out,
why does he bow down to compassion
and says it creates wisdom?
That's confusing.
DE GSUM GYI NANG NAS
SNYING RJE GTZO BO NYID DU
BSTAN PAR BZHED NAS,
Chandrakirti wants to say
that of bodhichitta, and the
direct perception of emptiness,
and compassion,
compassion is the most important.
That's the root.
GTZO BO NYID means like,
we have it in LAM GTZO RNAM GSUM,
Three Principle Paths.
The main one is compassion.
BZHED NAS, GANG PHYIR ZHES SOGS GSUNGS SO,
That's why he wrote this verse.
We can see a picture here of a tree
with a bunch of big roots.
And I was trying to find a thing,
it's like the one root
which leads to the two roots
which leads to the tree.
The tree is Buddhahood
and nirvana.
The two roots are
perceiving emptiness and bodhichitta.
And the root of those
is compassion.
Great.
So I've tried to find a
picture for that, good luck.
This is the closest I can find.
All right.
Now let's go back to the text.
Then Tsongkapa uses the
verse, he quotes the verse.
Now I'm going to skip to GANG GI PHYIR.
GANG GI PHYIR SNYING BRTZE
BA NI RGYAL BA'I LO TOG
PHUN TSOGS 'DI'I
You can think of
Buddhas as the crops.
You can think of Buddha as the fruit tree.
Pachi, what were the main
trees you guys planted in
Costa Rica?
Any fruit trees? Coffee trees? No.
Mix of everything.
Let's do coffee tree
cause I'm in the mood.
Coffee tree or coffee bush
really? Bush, I guess.
So Buddhahood is the coffee bush.
I guess.
Doesn't quite fit.
It's more like crops.
Let's say corn.
THOG MAR SKYED PA LA GAL
CHE BA SA BON DANG NI 'DRA
The first thing you need
for a tree is a seed.
Therefore, you need compassion.
BAR DU, in the middle,
GONG NAS GONG DU SPEL BA LA CHU DANG 'DRA
In between, compassion is important
because it's like the water
that you put on the seed.
THA MAR GDUL BYAS YUN RING
DU LONGS SPYOD PA'I GNAS LA
And in the end, after
the fruit tree grows,
people can eat those mangoes forever.
Buddhahood GNAS LA.
'BRAS BU'I SMIN PA LTA BUR
'DOD PAR GYUR PA DE'I PHYIR,
ZLA BA'I ZHABS BDAG GIS NYAN
RANG DANG SANGS RGYAS DANG,
BYANG SEMS DANG DE'I RGYU
GZHAN GNYIS LAS KYANG
THOG MAR RAM, BSTAN
BCOS RTZOM BA'I THOG MAR
SNYING RJE CHEN PO LA BSTOD PAR BGYI'O
I'm going to, Chandrakirti is saying
I'm bowing down at the
beginning of my book
not to the perception of emptiness
and not to bodhichitta,
but to the cause for both of those,
which is compassion.
Because this is the
opening verse of that book,
which is the mother book of
all emptiness books in Tibetan.
Let's go to the next line, next paragraph.
DE YANG DA GZOD BSTOD
PA MIN GYI DE MA THAG TU
RGYAL BA'I LO TOG BSKRUN PA LA,
THOG MTHA' BAR GSUM DU GAL
CHE BAR BSTAN PA DE NYID DE,
NYID KYI SGRAS NI DPE'I
SKABS SU PHYI'I LO TOG LA
THOG MTHA' BAR GSUM
The point of this next paragraph
is that Chandrakirti says,
"Love and only love is the main root."
Love and only love is the main root.
And when he means is, yes
I'm comparing love
to three stages in the
growth of a fruit tree.
I'm comparing love
to three stages
in the growth of a fruit tree.
But please remember, I'm
talking about the same love.
The seed is the love.
The water is the love.
The fruit of the tree is the love.
All three are love.
Sorry, compassion.
All right.
I'm going to start the next paragraph.
Oh, you have a picture here
of a tree and some fruits,
or some flowers on the tree.
Yeah, I took this picture
at my house a few days ago,
and I planted a peach tree.
I planted two peach
trees at the Black Hole,
I mean, the Peach Tree Cafe.
Then I had an extra one, so I took it home
and I planted it there.
It just grew very well and
this is the first year.
Usually you don't get
fruit the first year.
But it flowered, the whole tree flowered
the first year.
So it's a baby, baby, baby tree.
But these are the flowers.
So, when you look at that picture,
you can think about the
flowers are like the
fruit of the tree.
The tree is the... and
then there's the water
that I put on the tree all winter.
And then there's the seed,
the peach pit, from
which we grew the tree.
All right, we're going to
start now, Pau, with THOG MAR.
It's the paragraph that
begins with THOG MAR.
THOG MAR GAL CHE BA LA
SA BON LTA BU YIN TSUL
What's important at the beginning
is you've got to have a seed.
'DI LTAR SNYING RJE CHEN PO
CAN NI SEMS CAN GYI SDUG BSGNAL
GYIS SDUG BSNGAL BAS, SDUG
BSNGAL CAN GYI SEMS CAN THAMS CAD
BSKYAB PA'I PHYIR DU
If you want to take care
of all living beings
who are suffering like your mom
who's blind and went crazy and
is about to fall off a cliff,
BDAG GIS SEMS CAN 'DI THAMS CAD 'KHOR BA'I
SDUG BSNGAL NAS BTON TE
I'm going to get all
of these living beings
out of sansara.
SANGS RGYAS LA NGES PAR SBYAR BAR BYA'O
I will get them to enlightenment.
BYA BA LA DMIGS PA'I SEMS BSKYED LA
So isn't that the essence of bodhichitta?
So that's easy. You have to
want to get people out of pain
if you want to reach Buddhahood
to help all living beings.
First, you have to want to
get them out of trouble.
Then you can have bodhichitta.
So first, you've got to have compassion
and then you can have bodhichitta.
And I would say,
first, you have to feel their pain
before you can want to get
them out of their pain.
First, you have to feel...
First you have to feel what
the other person is feeling
before you want to save them.
So bodhichitta is like
you want to save them.
But first you have to
feel what they're feeling.
Otherwise, you won't want to save them.
You have to imagine what it's like to be
crazy, and blind, and
up on a mountain cliff
before you can try to help your mom.
You have to imagine how she feels,
how it feels to be your mom.
All right.
But we're waiting for,
I don't know about you,
Pau and Pachi, Cristina,
I'm waiting to see
how's he going to connect
it to seeing emptiness?
I can understand the bodhichitta part.
Let's keep going.
DE YANG RANG GIS SANGS RGYAS THOB PA LA
RAG LAS PAR MTHONG NAS
Well, if I really want to help my mom,
I have to have the power to help my mom.
And for that, I need to become a Buddha.
BDAG GIS 'DI RNAMS KYI DON
DU BLA MED BYANG CHUB CI NAS
KYANG THOB PAR BYA'O
So I'm going to have to become a Buddha.
Okay, that's clear.
BYANG CHUB LA DMIGS PA'I
SEMS NGES PAR BSKYED DO
So don't forget, sometimes bodhichitta
is called the state of
mind with two focuses.
What are they?
I'm focused on
others and I want to achieve
Buddhahood. So it's called
the mind with two focuses.
Sometimes bodhichitta is called
Now, as far as this part
about achieving Buddhahood,
okay, I want to help everybody
so I'm going to have
to achieve Buddhahood.
Next paragraph.
I have this picture I found, I don't know,
it's kind of pushing it, right?
In DCI, we call it...
What do you call that?
Reverse engineering?
I used to go to Switzerland
for jewelry shows.
And there'll be 10,000
people there showing jewelry.
Unbelievable. Basel,
Switzerland. Every year.
People will go there to buy jewelry,
but manufacturers will go there to buy
other company's jewelry and steal it.
So you see,
you go to the trade show,
the audiences are massing
in front of one new product,
and you go and buy one.
Even though it helps your competition,
you buy one.
Even if it's $10,000, you buy one.
And you take it home
and you take it apart,
and you figure out how did they make it.
That's called reverse engineering.
And it's very, very common in everything,
every kind of product.
You go buy the latest printer
and then you take it
apart and you figure out
how to copy it.
So anyway, that's called
reverse engineering.
So what I'm saying is,
let's start with enlightenment
and let's work backwards to bodhichitta
and emptiness perception,
and then we'll work
backwards to compassion.
DE 'DRA BA'I DAM BCA' BA DE
YANG GNYIS SU MED PA'I YE SHES
KYIS MTSON PA'I SBYIN SOGS KYI
SPYOD PA DOR NA MI 'GRUB PAR
You can not...
Now here's the emptiness one.
$100 to whoever can tell it to me first.
You ready?
By the way, I'm not offering
it to everybody at home,
I'm just offering it to the people here.
$100.
Here's the sentence where
Tsongkapa explains our question,
but it's not obvious.
DE 'DRA BA'I DAM BCA' BA DE
Look, you made a promise, right?
What?
I'm going to achieve
enlightenment for all my moms.
Well, for that, you're
going to have to practice
the six perfections.
Therefore, emptiness.
Come on, $100.
Come on. Just say something.
[Student] Understand emptiness.
[GMR] I'll say it again.
Here's what he says.
To fulfill the wish of bodhichitta,
you're going to have to become a Buddha.
To become a Buddha, you're
going to have to follow
the six perfections.
That's why I say emptiness is the root.
[Student] (unclear)
[GMR] Connected to the perfection.
[Student] One feels what
another feels. [GMR] No.
[Student] ...because you
see emptiness. [GMR] No.
Okay, for $50.
The sixth perfection is
said to be the result,
sorry,
the first five perfections
are said to be the result
of the sixth perfection.
Practicing giving, for example,
is only a perfection if you do it with...
[Student] emptiness.
[GMR] Yay! So that's a 20 dollars answer.
Okay, $20 answer.
Isn't that cool?
So he says, "Ah, the mystery is solved."
- What mystery?
- Supposedly compassion is
the root of seeing emptiness?
- Yeah.
- Why?
- Compassion wants to become a Buddha.
- Okay.
- That means compassion wants
to practice the 6 perfections.
- Okay.
- But a perfection is not a
perfection unless you do it with
emptiness perception.
Therefore, compassion leads to
Because compassion leads to the intention
of practicing emptiness,
so you can become a Buddha.
Got it?
Yay!
Okay, the mystery is solved.
KHO NAR 'JUG PAS NA,
We can skip the rest of that sentence.
Let's go to the
last line here.
The last verse here.
And he's going back to Arya Nagarjuna's
String of Jewels, Ratnavali.
vāli or valī, I don't know.
We're going back to the
String of Precious Jewels by
Arya Nagarjuna.
And here's our final
verse for our class.
DON 'DI LA DGONGS NAS
RIN CHEN 'PHRENG BA LAS
Arya Nagarjuna is talking
about the same idea
in his String of Precious Jewels
when he says,
,THEG PA CHEN PO GANG ZHIG LAS,
,SNYING RJE SNGON BTANG SPYOD KUN DANG,
,YE SHES DRI MA MED BSHAD PA,
,SEMS YOD SU ZHIG DE LA SMOD,
He says,
"you guys, if you have
any brains at all..."
This is very Nagarjuna,
the last line. SEMS YOD
SEMS YOD -- If you have any brains at all,
you should study the Mahayana.
You should go straight to
the compassion vehicle.
And what's that one?
Oh, it includes compassion
and wisdom.
It includes compassion and wisdom.
Mahayana is just wisdom
married to compassion.
That's all.
THEG PA CHEN PO GANG ZHIG LAS
And if you think that's a dumb idea,
you ain't got any brains.
SEMS YOD SU ZHIG DE LA SMOD means,
if you think it's a dumb idea
to combine wisdom with compassion,
to reach Buddhahood and bodhichitta,
then I'm afraid you don't
got any brains at all.
All right, we finished the class.
Good job you guys.
Good job on the tech side
and the Sanskrit side.
Thank you.
And we'll see you guys in the next class.
Yay!